Why can't we solve these problems?
لماذا لا نستطيع حل هذه المشاكل؟
We know what they are.
نعرف ماهيتها.
Something always seems to stop us.
يبدو أن شيء ما يوقفنا دائما.
Why?
لماذا؟
I remember March the 15th, 2000.
أتذكر الخامس عشر من مارس 2000.
The B15 iceberg broke off the Ross Ice Shelf.
انفصل الجبل الجليدي B15 عن الجرف الجليدي روس.
In the newspaper it said
وفي الصحيفة قيل أن
"it was all part of a normal process."
"كل ذلك جزء من عملية طبيعية."
A little bit further on in the article
لاحقا في المقال
it said "a loss that would normally take
يقول "خسارة تستغرق عادة
the ice shelf 50-100 years to replace."
من الجرف الجليدي 50 إلى 100 سنة لتعويضها."
That same word, "normal,"
تلك الكلمة نفسها، "عادي،"
had two different,
كان لها معنيان مختلفان،
almost opposite meanings.
ومتضادان تقريبا.
If we walk into the B15 iceberg
إن صادفنا الجبل الجليدي B15
when we leave here today,
حين نغادر هنا اليوم،
we're going to bump into something
سنصطدم بشيء
a thousand feet tall,
بعلو ألف قدم،
76 miles long,
وطول 76 ميلا،
17 miles wide,
و17 ميلا في العرض،
and it's going to weigh two gigatons.
وسيزن 2 جيغا طن .
I'm sorry, there's nothing normal about this.
أنا آسف، ليس هناك شيء عادي بخصوص هذا.
And yet I think it's this perspective of us
ومع ذلك أعتقد أن مقاربتنا
as humans to look at our world
كبشر في النظر إلى العالم
through the lens of normal
من خلال عدسة المفهوم " العادي "
is one of the forces
هي إحدى القوى
that stops us developing real solutions.
التي توقفنا من تطوير حلول حقيقية.
Only 90 days after this,
90 يوما فقط بعد هذا،
arguably the greatest discovery
يمكن القول أن أعظم اكتشاف
of the last century occurred.
في القرن الماضي قد حصل.
It was the sequencing for the first time
وقد كان السلسلة للمرة الأولى
of the human genome.
للجينوم البشري.
This is the code that's in every single one
هذه هي الشيفرة الموجودة في كل واحدة من
of our 50 trillion cells
ال50 ترليون خلية لدينا
that makes us who we are and what we are.
والتي تجعلنا من نحن عليه وما نحن عليه.
And if we just take one cell's worth
وإن أخذنا مقدار خلية واحدة فقط
of this code and unwind it,
من هذه الشيفرة وقمنا ببسطها،
it's a meter long,
إنها بطول متر واحد،
two nanometers thick.
وبسمك 2 نانومتر.
Two nanometers is 20 atoms in thickness.
2 نانومتر تعادل سمك 20 ذرة
And I wondered,
وتساءلت،
what if the answer to some of our biggest problems
ماذا إن كان الجواب لبعض أكبر مشاكلنا
could be found in the smallest of places,
يمكن إيجاده في أصغر الأماكن،
where the difference between what is
حيث الفرق بين ما هو
valuable and what is worthless
ما قيمة له وما لا قيمة له
is merely the addition or subtraction
هي مجرد إضافة أو حذف
of a few atoms?
بضع ذرات؟
And what
وماذا
if we could get exquisite control
لو أمكننا الحصول على سيطرة بديعة
over the essence of energy,
على أساس الطاقة،
the electron?
الإلكترون؟
So I started to go around the world
وهكذا بدأت في السفر حول العالم
finding the best and brightest scientists
بحثا عن أفضل وألمع العلماء
I could at universities
المتوفرين في الجامعات
whose collective discoveries have the chance
والذين لاكتشافاتهم الجماعية الفرصة
to take us there,
لأخذنا هناك،
and we formed a company to build
وأنشأنا شركة للبناء
on their extraordinary ideas.
على أفكارهم الاستثنائية.
Six and a half years later,
بعد سنتين ونصف،
a hundred and eighty researchers,
مئة وثمانون باحثا،
they have some amazing developments
لديهم بعض التطويرات المذهلة
in the lab,
في المختبر،
and I will show you three of those today,
سأريكم ثلاثة منها اليوم،
such that we can stop burning up our planet
بحيث نتوقف عن حرق كوكبنا
and instead,
وبدل ذلك،
we can generate all the energy we need
يمكننا توليد كل الطاقة التي نحتاجها
right where we are,
تماما حيث نحن،
cleanly, safely, and cheaply.
بنظافة، وأمان، وثمن بخس.
Think of the space that we spend
فكروا في الفضاء الذي نقضي
most of our time.
فيه معظم وقتنا.
A tremendous amount of energy
كمية هائلة من الطاقة
is coming at us from the sun.
تأتينا من الشمس.
We like the light that comes into the room,
يعجبنا الضوء الذي يدخل الغرفة،
but in the middle of summer,
لكن في عز الصيف،
all that heat is coming into the room
كل ذلك الحر يأتي إلى الغرفة
that we're trying to keep cool.
والذي نحاول إبقائها باردة.
In winter, exactly the opposite is happening.
في الشتاء، العكس تماما يحصل.
We're trying to heat up
نحن نحاول تسخين
the space that we're in,
المكان الذي نحن فيه،
and all that is trying to get out through the window.
وكل ذلك يحاول الخروج من النافذة.
Wouldn't it be really great
ألن يكون من الرائع
if the window could flick back the heat
لو أن النافذة بإمكانها إعادة رد الحرارة
into the room if we needed it
إلى الغرفة إن احتجنا إليها
or flick it away before it came in?
أو إبعادها قبل أن تأتي؟
One of the materials that can do this
أحد المواد التي يمكنها القيام بهذا
is a remarkable material, carbon,
هي مادة استثنائية، الكربون،
that has changed its form in this incredibly beautiful reaction
والتي غيرت شكلها في هذا التفاعل الغاية في الجمال
where graphite is blasted by a vapor,
حيث يفجر الغرافيت بالبخار،
and when the vaporized carbon condenses,
وحين يتكثف الكربون المبخر،
it condenses back into a different form:
يتكثف في شكل مختلف:
chickenwire rolled up.
السياج المتشابك ملتف.
But this chickenwire carbon,
لكن كربون السياج المتشابك هذا،
called a carbon nanotube,
المسمى أنابيب نانوية كربونية،
is a hundred thousand times smaller
هي أصغر بمئات ألوف المرات
than the width of one of your hairs.
من عرض إحدى شعيراتكم.
It's a thousand times
إنه أكثر بآلاف المرات
more conductive than copper.
في التوصيل الكهربائي من النحاس.
How is that possible?
كيف يكون ذلك ممكنا؟
One of the things about working at the nanoscale
أحد الأمور بخصوص العمل على مستوى النانو
is things look and act very differently.
هو أن الأشياء تبدو وتتصرف بشكل مختلفا جدا.
You think of carbon as black.
تفكرون في الكربون على أنه أسود.
Carbon at the nanoscale
الكربون في المستوى النانوي
is actually transparent
هو في الواقع شفاف
and flexible.
ومرن.
And when it's in this form,
وحين لا يكون على هذا الشكل،
if I combine it with a polymer
حين أدمجه مع بوليمر
and affix it to your window
وألصقه بنافذتكم
when it's in its colored state,
حين يكون في وضعيته الملونة،
it will reflect away all heat and light,
سيقوم دائما بعكس كل الحر والضوء،
and when it's in its bleached state
وحين يكون في حالته المبيضة
it will let all the light and heat through
سيسمح للضوء والحر بالدخول
and any combination in between.
وكل تركيبة في ما بين الحالتين.
To change its state, by the way,
تغيير حالته، بالمناسبة،
takes two volts from a millisecond pulse.
يحتاج فولتين من ذبذبة ميلوثانية.
And once you've changed its state, it stays there
وحين تتغير حالته يبقى كذلك
until you change its state again.
حتى تغير حالته مجددا.
As we were working on this incredible
ونحن نعمل على هذا الاكتشاف المذهل
discovery at University of Florida,
في جامعة فلوريدا،
we were told to go down the corridor
قيل لنا أن نذهب نزولا في الرواق
to visit another scientist,
لزيارة عالم آخر،
and he was working
وقد كان يعمل
on a pretty incredible thing.
على أمر في غاية الروعة.
Imagine
تخيلوا
if we didn't have to rely
إن لم يكن من الضروري علينا الاعتماد
on artificial lighting to get around at night.
على الإضاءة الصناعية للتنقل ليلا.
We'd have to see at night, right?
سيكون علينا أن نبصر في الليل، صحيح؟
This lets you do it.
هذا يسمح لكم بالقيام بذلك.
It's a nanomaterial, two nanomaterials,
إنها مادة نانوية، مادتان نوويتان،
a detector and an imager.
ملتقط ومصور.
The total width of it
عرضه الإجمالي
is 600 times smaller
هو أصغر ب600 مرة
than the width of a decimal place.
من عرض جزء عشري.
And it takes all the infrared available at night,
ويأخذ كل الأشعة فوق الحمراء المتوفرة ليلا،
converts it into an electron
ويحولها إلى إلكترون
in the space of two small films,
في فضاء فيلمين صغيرين،
and is enabling you to play an image
ويسمح لك بإظهار صورة
which you can see through.
يمكنك النظر من خلالها.
I'm going to show to TEDsters,
سأعرض على التيدسترز" نشطاء تيد "،
the first time, this operating.
أول مرة، هذا الإكتشاف
Firstly I'm going to show you
أولا سأعرض عليكم
the transparency.
الشفافية.
Transparency is key.
الشفافية هي مفتاح.
It's a film that you can look through.
إنه فيلم يمكنكم النظر من خلاله.
And then I'm going to turn the lights out.
ثم سأقوم بإطفاء الأضواء.
And you can see, off a tiny film,
ويمكنكم الرؤية، من خلال فيلم دقيق،
incredible clarity.
وضوحا هائلا.
As we were working on this, it dawned on us:
ونحن نعمل على هذا، اتضح لنا:
this is taking infrared radiation, wavelengths,
هذا يأخذ الإشعاعات التحت حمراء، الطول الموجي،
and converting it into electrons.
ويحوله إلى إلكترونات.
What if we combined it
ماذا لو دمجناه
with this?
مع هذا؟
Suddenly you've converted energy
فجأة نكون حولنا الطاقة
into an electron on a plastic surface
إلى إلكترون على سطح بلاستيكي
that you can stick on your window.
يمكنكم لصقه على نافذتكم.
But because it's flexible,
لكن لأنه مرن،
it can be on any surface whatsoever.
يمكنه أن يكون على أي سطح كيفما كان.
The power plant of tomorrow
محطة توليد الكهرباء في الغد
is no power plant.
هي انعدام محطات توليد كهرباء.
We talked about generating and using.
تحدثنا عن التوليد والاستخدام.
We want to talk about storing energy,
نريد الحديث عن تخزين الطاقة،
and unfortunately
لكن لسوء الحظ
the best thing we've got going
أفضل ما لدينا
is something that was developed in France
هو شيء تم تطويره في فرنسا
a hundred and fifty years ago,
قبل مئة وخمسين عاما،
the lead acid battery.
البطارية الحمضية.
In terms of dollars per what's stored,
من حيث قيمة ما تم تخزينه بالدولارات،
it's simply the best.
إنها بكل بساطة الأفضل.
Knowing that we're not going to put fifty of
مع العلم أننا لن نضع خمسين منها
these in our basements to store our power,
في قبونا لتخزين الطاقة،
we went to a group at University of Texas at Dallas,
توجهنا إلى مجموعة في جامعة تكساس في دالاس،
and we gave them this diagram.
وأعطيناهم هذا الرسم البياني.
It was in actually a diner
كان ذلك في الواقع أثناء عشاء
outside of Dallas/Fort Worth Airport.
خارج مطار دالاس/فورث وورث.
We said, "Could you build this?"
قلنا، "هل في مقدورك بناء هذا؟"
And these scientists,
وهؤلاء العلماء،
instead of laughing at us, said, "Yeah."
بدل أن يضحكوا علينا، قالو، "نعم."
And what they built was eBox.
وما بنوه كان eBox.
EBox is testing new nanomaterials
الeBox يقوم بتجربة مواد نانوية جديدة
to park an electron on the outside,
لركن إلكترون في الخارج،
hold it until you need it,
والاحتفاظ به حتى تحتاجه،
and then be able to release it and pass it off.
ثم تكون قادرا على إطلاقه وتفريقه.
Being able to do that means
أن تكون قادرا على القيام بذلك يعني
that I can generate energy
أنه بمقدوري توليد الطاقة
cleanly, efficiently and cheaply
بنظافة، وفاعلية وبثمن بخس
right where I am.
تماما حيث أنا.
It's my energy.
إنها طاقتي.
And if I don't need it, I can convert it
وحين لا أحتاجها، يمكنني تحويلها
back up on the window
رجوعا نحو النافذة
to energy, light, and beam it,
إلى طاقة، ضوء، وإرسال شعاع،
line of site, to your place.
في خط مستقيم إلى مكانك.
And for that I do not need
ومن أجل ذلك لا أحتاج
an electric grid between us.
إلى شبكة كهربائية بيننا.
The grid of tomorrow is no grid,
محطات توليد الكهرباء في الغد هي انعدام محطات التوليد،
and energy, clean efficient energy,
والطاقة، الطاقة النظيفة والفعالة،
will one day be free.
ستكون يوما ما مجانية.
If you do this, you get the last puzzle piece,
إن قمتم بذلك، ستحصلون على آخر قطعة من الأحجية،
which is water.
والتي هي الماء.
Each of us, every day,
جميعنا، يوميا،
need just eight glasses of this,
نحتاج فقط ثمانية أكواب من هذا،
because we're human.
لأننا بشر.
When we run out of water,
حين ينفذ لدينا الماء،
as we are in some parts of the world
كما حصل في مناطق من العالم
and soon to be in other parts of the world,
وقريبا سيحصل في مناطق أخرى من العالم،
we're going to have to get this from the sea,
سيكون علينا الحصول على هذا من البحر،
and that's going to require us to build desalination plants.
وهذا سيحتم علينا بناء محطات تحلية للمياه.
19 trillion dollars is what we're going to have to spend.
19 ترليون دولا هي ما سيكون علينا صرفه.
These also require tremendous amounts of energy.
هذا يتطلب كذلك مقدار هائلا من الطاقة.
In fact, it's going to require twice the world's
في الواقع، سيتطلب ضعف مخزون العالم
supply of oil to run the pumps
من النفط لتشغيل المضخات
to generate the water.
لتوليد المياه.
We're simply not going to do that.
لن نقوم بذلك بكل بساطة.
But in a world where energy is freed
لكن في عالم تكون فيه الطاقة مجانية
and transmittable
وقابلة للنقل
easily and cheaply, we can take any water
بكل سهولة وتكلفة رخيصة، يمكننا أخذ أي مياه
wherever we are
أينما كنا
and turn it into whatever we need.
وتحويله إلى ما نحتاجه.
I'm glad to be working with
أنا سعيد بالاشتغال مع
incredibly brilliant and kind scientists,
مع علماء باهرين ولطفاء،
no kinder than
ليسوا أكثر لطفا من
many of the people in the world,
الكثير من الناس في العالم،
but they have a magic look at the world.
لكن لديهم نظرة ساحرة للعالم.
And I'm glad to see their discoveries
وأنا سعيد لرؤية اكتشافاتهم
coming out of the lab and into the world.
تخرج من المختبر إلى العالم.
It's been a long time in coming for me.
لقد استغرق ذلك مني وقتا طويلا.
18 years ago,
قبل 18 سنة،
I saw a photograph in the paper.
رأيت صورة فوتوغرافية في الجريدة.
It was taken by Kevin Carter
تم التقاطها من طرف كيفن كارتر
who went to the Sudan
الذي ذهب إلى السودان
to document their famine there.
لتوثيق مجاعتهم هناك.
I've carried this photograph with me
وقد كنت أحمل هذه الصورة معي
every day since then.
يوميا منذ ذلك الحين.
It's a picture of a little girl dying of thirst.
إنها صورة طفلة صغيرة تموت من العطش.
By any standard this is wrong.
بكل المعايير هذا خاطئ.
It's just wrong.
إنه فقط خاطئ.
We can do better than this.
نستطيع القيام بما هو أفضل من هذا.
We should do better than this.
علينا القيام بما هو أفضل من هذا.
And whenever I go round
وأينما ذهبت
to somebody who says,
إلى من يقول،
"You know what, you're working on something that's too difficult.
"تعرف ماذا، أنت تعمل على أمر في غاية الصعوبة.
It'll never happen. You don't have enough money.
لن يحدث ذلك أبدا. ليس لديك المال الكافي.
You don't have enough time.
ليس لديك الوقت الكافي.
There's something much more interesting around the corner,"
هناك أمر مثير أكثر على الأبواب،"
I say, "Try saying that to her."
أقول، "جرب أن تقول ذلك لها."
That's what I say in my mind. And I just say
هذا ما أقوله في ذهني. وأقول فقط
"thank you," and I go on to the next one.
"شكرا لك،" وأذهب إلى الشخص التالي.
This is why we have to solve our problems,
من أجل هذا علينا حل مشاكلنا،
and I know the answer as to how
وأعرف الجواب بخصوص كيفية
is to be able to get exquisite control
الحصول على القدرة على التحكم المتقن
over a building block of nature,
في المكونات الأساسية للطبيعة،
the stuff of life:
أشياء الحياة:
the simple electron.
الإلكترون البسيط.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)